Joan McBreen papers
Emory University
Joan McBreen papers,1979-2007
McBreen, Joan, 1944-
Manuscript Collection No. 1088
17.75 linear ft. (38 boxes), 2 oversized papers (OP), and 3 bound volumes (BV)
Papers of Irish poet Joan McBreen, including correspondence, writings, photographs, audiovisual material and printed material.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 2008.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Series 7: Use copies have not been made for all of the audiovisual series at this time. Researchers must contact MARBL in advance for access to these materials.
Series 11: Born digital materials are closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Joan McBreen, Irish poet and teacher, was born in 1944 in Sligo, Ireland to Bernard and Patricia Collery. She attended Sion Hill Froebel College of Education and the National University of Ireland, and in 1970 married Joe McBreen. They have six children: Brian, Jody, Sarah, Helen, Peter, and Adrian. McBreen was a primary school teacher from 1966 to 1986, when she quit her position in order to pursue her career as a poet.
In 1990, McBreen published her first volume of poetry, The Wind Beyond the Wall. Subsequent volumes followed, including A Walled Garden in Moylough (1995), Winter in the Eye: New and Selected Poems (2003), and Heather Island (2009). McBreen earned a degree in Women's Studies from the University of Dublin in 1997, and her master's dissertation research focused on modern Irish women poets. This research informed her role as editor of The White Page: Twentieth-Century Irish Women Poets, an anthology she published in 1999. She has also edited The Watchful Heart: A New Generation of Irish Poets, Poems and Essays (2009), an anthology featuring the work of twenty-four Irish poets born in the last fifty years. In 2004, she released a CD entitled The Long Light on the Land-Selected Poems, which included McBreen reading her poetry to a background of traditional Irish music.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the personal and literary papers of Joan McBreen from 1979-2007, documenting her career as a poet, anthology editor, and advocate for the increased awareness of Irish women poets. The papers include correspondence, writings by McBreen, writings by others, subject files, printed material, photographs, audiovisual material, and born digital material.
Much of the correspondence is to and from poets, friends, and her publishers, and is of both a personal and professional nature. The writings are primarily comprised of personal notebooks, collected and uncollected poetry, and dissertation notes and research. In addition, the series also contains a substantial amount of material relating to McBreen's editorial work on The White Page. The writings by others series is comprised of manuscripts and typescripts sent to McBreen, and are largely made up of individual poems and poetry collections, in addition to a small number of screen plays and essay drafts. Subject files document McBreen's involvement in numerous literary festivals and workshops, and also include some personal records, in addition to files on topics such as Irish politics and literary figures. Printed material consists of published material by McBreen, about McBreen, and general printed items collected by her. Photographs consist primarily of publicity photographs of McBreen and photos of individual contributors to The White Page. Audiovisual material consists solely of cassettes of recordings by McBreen's friend and fellow poet, Anne Kennedy.
Arrangement Note
Organized into eight series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings, (3) Writings by others, (4) Subject files, (5) Printed material, (6) Photographs, (7) Audiovisual, and (8) Born digital material.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Brandes, Rand.; Grennan, Eamon, 1941-; Kennedy, Anne, 1935-1998.; Mason, David, 1954-; McGuckian, Medbh, 1950-; Newmann, Joan, 1942-; Mac Intyre, Tom, 1931-
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Women poets, Irish.
Form/Genre Terms
Audio recordings.; Manuscripts.; Poems.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1986-2007, Series 1; Boxes 1-8
  Scope and Content Note
  The correspondence series contains letters that McBreen wrote and received from 1986-2007. Much of the correspondence is of both a personal and professional nature; notable correspondents include poets and friends such as Rand Brandes, Eamon Grennan, Anne Kennedy, David Mason, Medbh McGuckian, Joan Newmann, and Tom; MacIntyre. A significant amount of the correspondence includes faxes to and from McBreen's North American publishers, Robert and Lysa McDowell of Story Line Press. In addition, there is correspondence between McBreen and Salmon Poetry, her Irish publisher. Also included are many acceptance and rejection letters from literary magazines and invitations for readings and lectures, which document the growth of McBreen's career through the 1990s and 2000s. Correspondence related to the research and publication of The White Page can be found in Subseries 2.3: Edited works.
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Undated [1 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Undated [2 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Undated [3 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Undated [4 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - February 1986-December 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January-December 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - January-July 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - August-December 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - January-April 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - May-September 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - October-December 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - January 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - February-March 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April-May 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - June-August 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - September-October 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - November 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - December 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - January-February 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - March-April 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - May-June 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - July-October 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - November-December 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - January-March 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - April 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - May-June 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - July-September 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - October-December 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - January-March 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - April-June 1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - July-September 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - October-December 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - January-July 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - August-December 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - January-June 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - July-December 1996 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - January-May 1997 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - June-December 1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - January-May 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - June-October 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - November 1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - December 1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - January-September 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - January 2001-December 2002 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - January-December 2003 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - January-August 2004 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - September 2004-October 2007 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Writings, 1986-2000, Series 2; Boxes 9-18
  The series contains Joan McBreen's published and unpublished writings from 1986 to 2000 and is comprised of personal notebooks, collected and uncollected poetry, edited works, and other writings.
  The notebook subseries (Subseries 2.1) includes notebooks that contain complete and partial poem manuscripts, literary notes and references, and personal reminders.
  The poems subseries (Subseries 2.2) includes manuscript and typescript drafts of McBreen's collected and uncollected poetry. The collected poetry (subseries 2.2a) is arranged in chronological order by book and contains multiple copies of the same poems, providing insight into McBreen's meticulous process of writing and rewriting/revising her poetry in order to craft a final version. The subseries also contains a considerable number of McBreen's uncollected poems (2.2b), featuring both manuscripts and typescripts that are arranged here in alphabetical order.
  McBreen's edited works (Subseries 2.3) consists of her editorial work on the poetry anthology, The White Page. This comprehensive study of contemporary Irish female poets features brief biographies and single poems by prominent poets, which are found in manuscript and typescript form in the individual author folders in the subseries. In addition, the author folders contain correspondence to and from McBreen, editorial corrections, and clippings. This subseries also contains general correspondence concerning the writing and publication of The White Page and a typescript draft of McBreen's editorial introduction to the anthology. Lastly, this subseries contains poem corrections, proof copies, contributor lists, and literary contact information for the 1999 publication.
  The final subseries (2.4), titled "Other Writings" is primarily comprised of McBreen's dissertation work, which later became the foundational research for her anthology, The White Page. In addition, the subseries also includes McBreen's Irish to English translations of a small number of poems, an interview typescript, a book review, an essay submission, a letter to the editor, and a formal introduction of fellow Irish female poets.
  Organized into four subseries: (2.1) Notebooks, (2.2) Poetry, (2.3) Edited works, and (2.4) Other writings.
  - Notebooks, 1987-1995, Subseries 2.1; Boxes 9-10
    The notebook subseries, spanning from the late 1980s to late 1990s, contains manuscript drafts of some of McBreen's collected and uncollected poems, literary notes and quotations, dated records of literary correspondence, and personal reminders. Although many of the notebooks have few writings, some allow insight into McBreen's creative writing process and her personal/academic literary interests.
    - Notebook [1], undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Notebook [2], undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Notebook [3], 1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Notebook [4], 1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Notebook [5], October 28, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Notebook [6], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Notebook [7], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Notebook [8], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Notebook [9], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Notebook [10], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Notebook [11], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Notebook [12], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Notebook [13], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Notebook [14], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Notebook [15], circa late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Notebook [16], 1990 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Notebook [17], 1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Notebook [18], circa early 1990s (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Notebook [19], circa early 1990s (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Notebook [20], circa early 1990s (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Notebook [21], 1990-1995 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Notebook [22], 1994 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Notebook [23], circa late 1990s (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Notebook [24], circa late 1990s (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Notebook [25], circa late 1990s (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Notebook [26], circa late 1990s (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Poems, 1986-1999, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 11-13
    The subseries includes manuscript and typescript drafts of McBreen's collected and uncollected poetry from 1986-1999. Of note to researchers is the thematic unity that runs throughout the entirety of the poetry subseries, centering on feelings of loss and renewal, familial memories and celebrations, local phenomena and politics, and the particularities of the Irish landscape. The collected poetry is arranged in chronological order by work, including McBreen's The Wind Beyond the Wall (1990), A Walled Garden in Moylough (1995), and Winter in the Eye: New and Selected Poems (2003). Many of the poems in this subseries have multiple drafts, providing researchers' insight into McBreen's meticulous process of writing and rewriting/revising her poetry in order to craft a final version.
    This subseries also contains a considerable number of McBreen's uncollected poems, which were composed in large part during the seven year gap (1996-2002) between the publication of the poet's A Walled Garden in Moylough and Winter in the Eye. Some uncollected poems, however, were composed in the late 1980s and early 1990. Although McBreen offers no explicit rationale for how poems were selected for various collections, it remains clear that the poet subjected her uncollected poetry to equally rigorous revision processes, as many folders in this subseries contain uncollected poems that were written and revised multiple times. The uncollected poems are written in both manuscript and typescript forms, and are arranged here in alphabetical order.
    Organized into two sections: (2.2a) Collected poems and (2.2b) Uncollected poems.
    - Collected poems, 1986-1999, Subseries 2.2a; Boxes 11-12
      Arranged in chronological order by date of publication; individual poems within the work are arranged in alphabetical order.
      - The Wind Beyond the Wall (1990)
      - "The Broken Swing," manuscripts and typescripts, May 17, 1987 [variant titles: "A Visit to St. John's Abbey," and "St. John's Abby"] (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - "Christmas in Tuam," typescripts, April 12, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - "Classibawn," typescripts, February 12, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - "Culleenamore," typescript, undated [variant title: "Return Visit to Culleenamore"] (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - "The Dark," typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - "Fall, 1987," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - "The Gift," manuscript and typescripts, undated [variant title: "Wedgewood"] (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - "Girl with Umbrella," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - "The Glory-Hole," manuscripts, undated [variant title: "Hide and Seek"] (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - "The Green Quilt," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - "The Hunter's Infidel," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - "The Left Hand," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - "The Master," manuscripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - "My Father," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - "My Grandmother," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - "My Space," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - "The Neighbours' Daughter," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - "The Night," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - "Once," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - "The Other Woman," typescripts, undated [variant title: "Another Woman"] (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - "The Peace-Keeper," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - "Poem for St. Brigid's Day," manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - "Primroses in March," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - "Rabbits," manuscripts and typescripts, November 18, 1987 [variant titles: "The Crow's Feather," and "Rhododendrons and Rabbits"] (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - "River Music," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - "The Saints," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - "The Stones," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - "The Straw Hat," manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
      - "Telephone Call," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
      - "Valkenswaard," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - "The Wedding Ring," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 31)
      - "Wild Woodbine," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
      - "The Wind Beyond the Wall," manuscripts and typescripts, September 20, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 33)
      - "The Woman and the Igloo," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 34)
      - "The Woman in the Yellow Dress," manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 35)
      - "The Woman in the Whitehorn Tree," typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
      - "Woman in Winter," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 37)
      - The Wind Beyond the Wall, bound typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 38)
      - The Wind Beyond the Wall, dedication and notes page (Box 11, Folder 39)
      - The Wind Beyond the Wall, uncorrected proof copy (Box 11, Folder 40)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough (1995)
      - "After Osip Mandelstam," manuscript and typescript, October 25, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 41)
      - "Ben Bulben," manuscripts and typescripts, February 13, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 42)
      - "Bog-Cotton," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 43)
      - "The Clean Slice," manuscript, undated [variant title: "Beyond the Garden's Solitude"] (Box 11, Folder 44)
      - "Dream of a Poet Child," typescripts, April 22, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 45)
      - "Eanach Cuain," manuscripts and typescripts, January 11, 1989 [variant title: "Remembering 'Eanach Cuain'-an Irish Lament"] (Box 11, Folder 46)
      - "Feathering the Room," manuscripts and typescripts, November 1-5, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 47)
      - "Fionnuala," manuscripts, January 25-28, 1994 [variant title: "Fionnuala's Lament"] (Box 11, Folder 48)
      - "Girl," typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 49)
      - "Hanging Wallpaper," manuscripts and typescripts, October 18, 1993-February 15, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 50)
      - "Heart in a Black Bowl," manuscripts and typescripts, June 8, 1991 [variant title: "Lover"] (Box 11, Folder 51)
      - "In a Suburban Garden on Christmas Night," typescripts, February 5, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 52)
      - "In the Brief Time Given," manuscript, February 1994 (Box 11, Folder 53)
      - "In the Daughter's Room," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 54)
      - "In Memoriam of JPB (1916-1993)," manuscript and partial typescript, April 26, 1993 [variant titles: "Winter," and "Death in April"] (Box 11, Folder 55)
      - "The Inner Room," typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - "The Iris Garden," typescript, June 22, 1992 [variant title: "In the Iris Garden"] (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - "Lettergesh," manuscripts and typescripts, June 3, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - "The Little Street," manuscripts and typescripts, March 31, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - "The Lost Brooch," manuscripts and typescripts, August-October, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - "The Mahogany Mirror in my Mother's Room," manuscript, January 26-27, 1992 [variant titles: "The Mahogany Mirror," and "I Wanted to Feel the Sun on my Skin"] (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - "Moore Hall in September," typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - "The Mountain Ash," manuscripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - "The Nest," typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - "The Notebook," manuscript and typescript, February 1994 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - "The Photograph of my Aunts," typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - "On Hearing my Daughter Play 'The Swan'," typescripts, April 2, 1992 [variant titles: "Chords" and "Swan"] (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - "On Reading Your Letter in June," manuscripts and typescripts, June 8, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - "Possibilities," typescripts, November 19, 1990 [variant title: "Postcards and Photograph on my Bedroom Mirror] (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - "Rose Cottage Finisklin, c 1995," typescripts, March 1991 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - "The Silken Robe," typescript, April 3, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - "Snow in September," typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - "Someone Should Tell My Mother," manuscripts and typescripts, May 1991 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - "This Light, This Silence," manuscripts and typescripts, November 7, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 19)
      - "Veronica," manuscripts and typescripts, May 16, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 20)
      - "Walking Barefoot on White Feathers," typescripts, March 6, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 21)
      - "A Walled Garden in Moylough," typescripts, May 10, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 22)
      - "Watches," manuscripts and typescripts, April 11, 1994 [variant titles: "The Bird Table," "The Man, the Watch and the Bird Table"] (Box 12, Folder 23)
      - "Winding the Wool," typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
      - "Woman Herding Cattle in a Field near Kilcolgan," typescript, March 26, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 25)
      - "Woman Watching the Door," manuscripts and typescripts, February-March 1993 (Box 12, Folder 26)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, proposed table of contents (Box 12, Folder 27)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, partial typescript draft, October 5, 1992 [includes poems: "Emma in Spring," "Sea Pinks on my Window Sill," "Winter Jasmine," "Silent Night," and "Near Doilin Strand, "Carraroe," and "Under the Trees" not included in final publication] (Box 12, Folder 28)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, partial typescript draft, January 27, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 29)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, typescript with corrections [contains typescript drafts that are not in the final version of published poetry collection] (Box 12, Folder 30)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, bound typescript draft, September 29, 1994 [includes variant title suggestions] (Box 12, Folder 31)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, notes (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - A Walled Garden in Moylough, page proofs, January 10-25, 1995 [includes editorial correspondence] (Box 12, Folder 33)
      - Winter in the Eye: New and Selected Poems (2003)
      - "The Bible Garden," manuscripts and typescripts, May 9, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 34)
      - "Camellia," manuscripts and typescripts, March 1998 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      - "A Cold May," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 36)
      - "Glassilaun," manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 37)
      - "The Half-Hearted Lament" manuscripts and typescripts, June 6, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 38)
      - "The Infinite," manuscript, September 24, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 39)
      - "The Other Side of the River," manuscripts, undated [variant title: "The Opposite Side of the River"] (Box 12, Folder 40)
      - "Poppies in Dominick Street," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
      - "Remembered Time," typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
      - "Silence is not a Space," February 21, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 43)
      - "The Terminology of Love," typescript, May 15, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 44)
      - "What We Have to Offer," page proof for The Literary Review, undated (Box 12, Folder 45)
      - "The Wisteria in the Courtyard of Dromore House," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Uncollected poems, 1986-1999, Subseries 2.2b; Box 13
      Arranged in alphabetical order.
      - "Afterwards," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - "Alaska," manuscripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - "August Evening on Galway Road," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - "Black Chairs," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - "The Blue Glass Necklace," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - "The Boy and the Moon," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - "The Bride," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "Bringing the News to Elizabeth," manuscripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - "The Caged Bird," typescripts, January 15, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - "Candles," manuscripts, December 4, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - "The Caves," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - "Christmas Memories," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - "A Clearer View," manuscripts and typescripts, November 19, 1994-January 22, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - "The Crippled Cross of Tuam," typescripts, April 28, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 14)